# ISRAT JAHAN

Graduate Fellow
Evolution, Ecology and Population Biology
Division of Biology and Biomedical Sciences
Washington University in St. Louis, St. Louis 63130
Email: isratjahan@wustl.edu

## **Research Interests**

I am broadly interested in how cooperation and conflict drive the evolution of complex life. Specifically, my empirical work focuses on the maintenance and transformation of multicellularity in the social amoebae *Dictyostelium discoideum*. The separation of unicellular and multicellular stages in *D. discoideum* life cycle allows me to investigate evolutionary pressures that shape complex social and life-history traits in multicellular development. My research is theoretically grounded in the principles of social evolution with scientific and philosophical implications for the major evolutionary transitions, germline vs somatic evolution, cell type development, and organismality.

### Education

### Washington University in St. Louis

In Progress

Doctor of Philosophy in Evolution, Ecology and Population Biology Advisor: Joan E. Strassmann, Ph.D. and David C. Queller, Ph.D.

## Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay

2018

Master of Science in Biotechnology

## University of Delhi

2016

Bachelor of Science in Biochemistry with Honors

## **Additional Learning**

## Janelia Evolution of Multicellularity Workshop, HHMI

October 2021

- Two-day online workshop focusing on the mechanisms and selective pressures driving the transition from unicellular to multicellular life
- Covered tools like single cell -omics, cell atlas, and conceptual approaches to understand multicellular regulation

## Data Carpentry Workshop on Genomics by the American Naturalists Graduate Council

July 2020

- Two-day workshop on genomic analysis of Next Generation Sequencing data
- Covered data wrangling and processing, quality control, alignment, variant calling

### Interdisciplinary Study of Cooperation Winter School, ASU

January 2020

- Lectures, seminars, and tutorials on fundamental processes underlying cooperation across diverse systems and disciplines
- Presented poster on Evolution of multicellularity in Dictyostelium discoideum

### **Publications**

**Jahan, I.** Larsen, T.J., Strassmann, J.E., and Queller, D.C. Group Maintenance in Aggregative Multicellularity, In: The evolution of multicellularity, eds. Herron, M.D., Conlin, P.L. and Ratcliff, W.C. CRC Press, 2021.

### Manuscript under preparation:

Larsen, T.J., **Jahan, I.**, Brock, D.A., Strassmann, J.E., and Queller, D.C. Reduced social function in experimentally evolved *Dictyostelium discoideum* implies selection for social conflict in nature. **Submission: November 2022** 

**Jahan, I.**, Scott, T.J., Larsen, T.J., Strassmann, J.E., and Queller, D.C. The evolution of a single celled propagule is insufficiently explained by Wolpert-Szathmary incompatibilities in a multicellular group. **Submission: December 2022** 

**Jahan, I.**, Inglis, F., Strassmann, J.E., and Queller, D.C. Germline sequestration in experimentally evolved pseudoorganisms under within and between organism selection. **Submission: 2023** 

Stephenson, C., **Jahan, I.,** Strassmann, J.E., and Queller, D.C. Life-history tradeoffs in *D. discoideum* under relaxed selection for social interactions. **Submission: 2023** 

## Awards, Honors, and Fellowships

## Guest in the "Paradox of the Organism" Work Group

2022- Present

Invited by Dr. Arvid Ågren and Dr. Manus Patten to participate in a Templeton Foundation funded work group on the "paradox of the organism".

#### McDonnell International Scholars Academy

- Funding for Ph.D. for 5 years (\$28,000 every year) 2018 Present
- Travel Allowance (\$2000 every year)
- Selected as Bayer Sponsored Fellow
   2021 Present

# Evolution Conference Registration Fee Waiver

June 2022

Student Travel Grant, ASU Interdisciplinary Study of Cooperation Winter SchoolJanuary 2020M.Sc. Fellowship (INR 80000) awarded by Department of Biotechnology, Govt. of India2016 – 2018All round Best Student of Daulat Ram College, University of Delhi2015

### **Seminars and Presentations**

| <ul> <li>Revisiting the "egg problem" in the evolution of multicellularity</li> </ul>              | November 2022  |
|--|----------------|
| Invited Speaker, Paradox of the Organism Conference, Georgetown University                         |                |
| <ul> <li>Seminar course at Georgetown University</li> </ul>  | September 2022 |
| Invited Panelist   |                |
| ■ The Evolution of Multicellularity  | January 2022   |
| Invited Speaker, Daulat Ram College, University of Delhi   |                |
| <ul> <li>Maintaining a cooperative group: Lessons from the social amoeba D. discoideum.</li> </ul> | November 2021  |
| Guest Lecturer, Harris Stowe State University, St. Louis (Animal Behavior class)                   |                |
| <ul> <li>Research Perspectives (BIO 4935)</li> </ul>   | September 2021 |
| Guest Lecturer, Washington University in St. Louis   |                |

# Research Experience

#### **Graduate Research**

Dissertation: Multicellularity and group maintenance in Dictyostelium discoidium
 Laboratory of Joan Strassmann, Ph.D., and David Queller, Ph.D.
 Department of Biology, Washington University in St. Louis

2019 - Present

Rotation Project: <u>Adaptation and bet hedging in yeast under fluctuating selection</u>
 Performed fitness assays for experimentally evolved yeast populations in the laboratory of Carlos Botero, Ph.D., Department of Biology, Washington University in St. Louis

Rotation Project: Molecular fossils from Pescadero Basin hydrothermal system

Extracted lipids hydrocarbons from carbonate samples to study early life in the laboratory of Alex Bradley, Ph.D., Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences, Washington University in St. Louis

#### M.Sc. Thesis

Dissertation: Biological and evolutionary study of different pathways taken by the

proteins of the relict plastid apicoplast in apicomplexan parasite Toxoplasma gondii

Advisor: Swati Patankar, Ph.D., Department of Biosciences and Bioengineering, IIT Bombay

Using techniques of human tissue culture, molecular cloning and confocal microscopy,

I showed that the apicoplast membrane protein APT1 does not take an evolutionarily

conserved golgi dependent pathway in Toxoplasma gondii.

### Undergraduate Research

Hands on training in Drosophila Resource Centre
 Project: Elucidation of dosage compensation over generations in *Drosophila melanogaster*.

 Innovation Project on Biomarkers of Heat Stress and Acclimatization 2014 – 2015

Project: Biochemical and physiological changes in heat stress and acclimation

DU Journal of Undergraduate Research, Vol 1, Issue 3, p49-56, 2015

## Mentorship

#### Peer Mentor for Graduate Students

2021 - 2022

Calum Stephenson and Ellen Urquhart First-year graduate students in the EEPB program, Washington University

### **Undergraduate Mentees**

Kayla Wallace, Strassmann-Queller Lab, Washington University

Sara Lichtarge, DBBS Summer Research Program

November 2020 – April 2021 June – August 2022

## Institute Student Mentorship Program, IIT Bombay

2017-2018

- Prepared Handbook for the Department of Biosciences
- Mentored five first-year MSc Biotechnology students at IIT Bombay
- As Department Coordinator, led a team of six and conducted institute wide post-graduate orientation for 1449 students

# Teaching Experience and Training

## Mentored Teaching Experience, Washington University in St. Louis

Behavioral Ecology (BIO 472)

Fall 2019

- Assistant to Instructor (Joan Strassmann, Ph.D.) for 34 students
- Leading Discussion section for 13 students

## Professional Development in Teaching Program

## Centre for Teaching and Learning, Washington University in St. Louis

Foundations in Teaching Workshops

August – October 2019

Teaching in an American Classroom

- Asking Questions to Improve Learning
- Designing and Delivering a Guest Lecture

## STEM Pedagogy workshops

December 2020

- Introduction to Pedagogical Scholarship
- Writing assignments in STEM

## **Academic Community Service**

#### Center for Diversity and Inclusion (WUSTL)

March 2021 – Present

Graduate Student Member of the Advisory Board

Steering Committee of Evolution, Ecology and Population Biology Program

2019 - 2021

Graduate Student representative

### OUT of the margins: A safe space discussion on sexuality and gender in nature

November 2021

- Organized a workshop with Dr. Anwesha Kundu
- Facilitated a discussion session with 20 International Scholars across the departments of Biomedical Sciences, Engineering, Law, Social Work, Economics, English, Political Science

### Neurodiversity and Allyship Seminar

April 2021

- Panelist for seminar by Neurodiversity at the Workplace
- Organized a training session with the help of Biology Inclusion Committee with 60 attendees
  across the departments of Biology, Chemistry, Physics, Earth & Planetary Sciences, Math & Statistics,
  and the Academy for Diversity, Equity, & Inclusion

## Science Education and Outreach

### Science at the Ferguson Farmers Market

September 2019

- Prepared short activities to teach basic evolution and ecology concepts to a general audience at a farmers' market booth
- Collaborated with Dr. Rachel Penczykowski and supervised a Red Queen card game to illustrate host-pathogen interactions

### Young Scientist Program

<u>Director of Finance</u>
 Served on the executive board and managed funds and grants for YSP finance

Continuing Mentor
 Mentored two high school students at Soldan International High School, St. Louis

## **Professional Associations**

| <ul> <li>American Society of Naturalists (awarded membership)</li> </ul>                  | 2022 – Present |
|---|----------------|
| <ul> <li>American Association for Advancement of Science (endorsed membership)</li> </ul> | 2020 - Present |
| <ul> <li>Society for Study of Evolution</li> </ul>  | 2018 – Present |
| <ul> <li>McDonnell International Scholar Academy</li> </ul>                               | 2018 – Present |

# **Programming Languages**

R, Python, Bash, C, NetLogo